[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
welcome everyone to the stowa i am
peter limberg the steward of the store
the stow is a place for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's edge
of this very moment so i see a few new
faces
here in the stone in the room just to
give you a brief
overview of what this strange place is
about
sometimes i call it a communal podcast
uh but we do have other
uh sessions like wisdom we have a wisdom
gym here
uh it's essentially a philosophical and
philosophical adjacent event
space um you can check out our website
for more events and we've been
we launched since covet happened and the
idea was to kind of respond to the
the mental health crisis the meaning
crisis the medic crisis
um and uh we've been going strong for
having
about 400 events since all for free on
the website
and we've been having really awesome
guests including
the one today i'm really excited to
introduce agnes callard
agnes is a philosophy professor at the
university of
chicago author of the book aspiration
the agency of
becoming and today um
she's going to share her thoughts on the
theme
can you know you are wrong and it's
going to be in two parts
i'll take her in a moment and she can
kind of explain how the the structure is
going to go but
she's going to essentially explain the
problem we're going to have a q a and
then we'll have another portion and then
follow up with the q
a having 60 minutes for the q a portion
if you have a question anytime you can
start throwing in the chat
now if you'd like um have a cue or
question before your question so i can
kind of spot it from the the
just the random comments um i'll call on
you and mute yourself
ask your question if you don't want to
be on youtube because this will
eventually be on youtube just indicate
that somewhere and then i'll read it on
your behalf
um so i think that's everything so that
being said
i will take you in agnes
oh you're in view right now oh okay
hi everyone um a special hello to
i noticed a few of my students usually
the students are here i just want to say
hi to aj
spencer victor and david north um
uh and uh nice to meet you to those of
you i haven't met before
so what i want to talk about today is um
a problem instead in some way like
unifies
um everything i worry about in
philosophy um
which is the problem of being able to
know that you're wrong
um and i thought
i asked peter to do this special
organization where we would spend
some time just talking about the problem
and then i'll talk about some solutions
that i've come up with to it
but i'm as interested in the problem as
i am in the solutions
okay the problem is that
like it's clear that people are
sometimes wrong about stuff right
we encounter all the time people have
false beliefs they're wrong um
so like that's probably happened to you
right you've probably been wrong in fact
you can probably think back
on a time when you're like oh i was
wrong about that um so it's like
a condition that a human being can be in
is to be wrong
but you can't know you're in that
condition you can't
experience it right because like you
know suppose i'm wrong
about like the weather outside so
suppose that i think
it's warm out but it's actually cold out
right it's like well i don't think i'm
wrong
because i think it's warm out and i
think i'm right about it's being worn
out
right um now i could go and check right
and then i like put my hand down i'm
like oh it's cold and like the second
that i correct that that very instant
like i
like as i feel the cold i'm like oh now
i think it's cold
i'm not i'm not wrong anymore right um
so it's like i can't catch myself being
wrong
um because as soon as i
realize i'm wrong i have the new belief
and i'm not wrong
right so as soon as i realize i'm wrong
about the weather i i now have what i
take to be the correct belief about the
weather
one way that philosophers think about
this problem is
uh something called moore's paradox
right uh
and moore's paradox um it's kind of this
observation
that you know um
you can someone can believe something
and that belief can be false right
and um so it can be
like you know suppose mike who's next to
me on the
zoom is mike believes falsely
um that it's um
cold right now in chicago okay so that
can be true
and like i can believe it right and i
can say it
but there's one person who can't say it
and it's mike
mike can't say oh it you know
it's um uh it's
it's cold right now in chicago but i
don't know that
right or you know i believe that
it's warm out in chicago though it isn't
right so
i can say that about mike but mike can't
say that about himself even though it
can be true
so there are true sentences like facts
about the world
that are unassertible by
certain people namely the people who
they're about right so that's what morse
and morse fredox is kind of a way of
expressing this problem about knowing
that you're wrong
it's like there are these unassertible
sentences right
you can also think of them as
unbelievable sentences like i
you know mike also can't have the
relevant belief he can't believe
it's warm in chicago but i don't believe
that he can't have that belief
right because if he thinks it's warm in
chicago he has that belief okay
but sort of more broadly you know a way
to
because you might you know i tried to i
tried to impress this paradox on my 16
year old and he's like
so what so there are some sentences you
can't assert you know whoever promised
you you were going to be able to assert
all the through sentences um
one way to think about it is just to
think about how much we identify
the people around us and these are both
people we're close to but almost kind of
especially
maybe like public figures or
intellectuals or whatever
in terms of like the stuff we think of
them as being wrong about
like there's a way in which someone's
errors almost like define the shape of
their point of view from your
perspective so when you think of them
you're like oh
he's the person who emphasizes this a
little too much or like
she you know kind of gets this wrong um
and and even with people that you're
close to you can probably pick out
you know it's almost like you pick out
their point of view by thinking
about what it is that they get a bit
wrong
but now it's like oh i can't know that
about myself like i can't pick myself
out
um so that's that's that's disturbing um
and um it is
uh it's like i'm kind of alienated
from myself in this way like everyone
else can
know the distinctive character of what
agnes is wrong about except
me i can't know that it's like i can
never know myself and so to me that's
like very
upsetting um and you know i feel like
there's
a lot of um
there's a lot of talk and
um let's almost like bluster that
happens because people can't deal with
this fact and they think that they can
solve the problem through a kind of
um metacognitive detachment like
well okay you know you should just you
should be humble
you should um you should always know
that you could be wrong
you shouldn't be too certain you should
be sort of skeptical
um don't be so sure of yourself don't be
overconfident
um uh
and like none of that none of that kind
of um
uh
attempt to take a step back from one's
point of view actually gives you
the thing that i'm disturbed that we
don't have
um which is it's almost like all of that
stuff all of that language that we
employ about being skeptical and being
distant and whatever
you know um it's like uh an attempt to
distance ourselves from our own
errors rather than to acknowledge them
um it's something
do you know this there's this game where
people put their hands like this
and you know you would put your hands to
mind and we push we try to push each
other over
right and there's this idea of like um
uh i think of the skeptical or
non-dogmatic
or self-critical people as the people
who are like really good at pulling
their hands away so they never fall over
it's like oh yeah just be really good at
detaching just like don't think anything
you think
um and then you're sort of like safe but
that's like to me that's like the wrong
direction it's not that we should try to
be safe from being wrong it's that we
want to know we want to be able to be
wrong and then know that we're wrong
um and like know what we're wrong about
concretely like i'm wrong about this
that's the thought i want to be able to
have like is it impossible for me to
have that thought is am i just
tragically faded to never have this
thing that i really want to have
that's the question so i thought we
could start and just talk about that
question and then i'll try and talk
about some
answers so i'm interested to hear your
responses and maybe solutions
beautiful so uh if you have any
questions start throwing them in the
chat we have some already
uh if you want me to read on your behalf
you just arrive just indicate that in
the chat
um let's start us off with rain
hi i'm so glad you're here i was a
couple minutes
late so i have the first question
apparently and i'm just
gonna dive in um a
a ship that's um on a course
is always pointed the wrong direction
mm-hmm you know there's a
yeah there's a moment there's a fraction
of a moment where it's pointed the right
direction
but then it's the wrong direction so
there's always this course correction
um and similarly from an embodied
cognitive standpoint
you know if i go to reach for something
or adjust my screen
i'm in a continual embodied feedback
loop with my environment
in order to constantly course correct so
it's not based on
on some kind of static propositions
about the world that
might be right or wrong it's just a
constant state of wrongness that's being
adjusted
so if one were to generalize that and
say
um that could that's broader than just
ships and
um reaching movements how
does uh the problem that you stated fit
in with this kind of view
good um so let me give like two
responses so the first
um um anyway i'm not complaining
that we're wrong like i i think we are
wrong about a lot of stuff all the time
and i'm not even trying to solve that
problem you might
you might worry someone might object to
me like why don't you solve that problem
instead why aren't you trying to be
right
and it's like no forget about that
problem i'm okay with being wrong i just
want to know that i'm wrong
okay so in effect that your point your
thought that like well we're always a
little bit off like i'm fine with that
but i want to be able to know it
i want to be able to be self-aware in
that moment of going the wrong way
that's the thing i want you to tell me
how i can get um the other thing i want
to say is that
you know when i was talking about the
various hand-wavy metacognitive detached
skeptical etc responses to this problem
which
are essentially ways of telling me like
um just stop asserting anything and then
you won't be wrong
um uh one of them is like oh everyone's
always wrong
like um there's another paradox in
philosophy called the preface
paradox where philosophers will start or
not just philosophers would be
start off their book by saying i'm sure
there's something in this book i'm wrong
about right
that for me that's like humility on the
cheap you know tell me what you're wrong
about i want to know that
um so the idea like that i can know in a
general sense that i'm
wrong about lots of stuff that's not
good enough for me
um uh i want to be able to be aware
concretely
of the specific things that i'm wrong
about
you have a follow-up ring
no thanks all right uh
heather you had a question
if you're gonna mute yourself
you could ask it but i will definitely
do it um i
am wondering what moore's law says about
um or what
comes out of moore's law in terms of
just cultivating humility
in general as an antidote to that um and
what i
you know whatever you have to say about
that i'd love to hear
yeah um
humility sadly um humility's not a
solution to moore's paradox um you can't
get out of it no matter how humble you
are
um i suppose except if you
avoided having any beliefs um
if you didn't have any beliefs then you
couldn't have any false beliefs
so um but um
uh so then there wouldn't you know
um on the other hand you still wouldn't
be able to say like there would still be
another a truth about you that you
couldn't say
you couldn't sit like there'd be like
some like
uh suppose i were the person with no
beliefs okay
so you guys could say um it's cold
outside but agnes doesn't believe that
but i can't say it i don't have any
beliefs but i also can't say
this thing i'm still wrong like because
i don't have this true belief that i
should have
right so really i can't you can't get
around worst paradox even by having no
beliefs because there's still going to
be these unassertible sentences
right that are true about you um about
the beliefs that you lack the true
beliefs that you lack
um uh and i guess more generally i feel
a little bit like humility goes in the
um uh sorry
that a lot of what people mean by
humility takes you in the opposite
direction from the direction i want to
go
like that's why i gave that sort of
metaphor of pushing the person over
like i want to i want to be pushed over
i don't want to be like really good at
pulling my hands away
um so and a lot of the like advice that
would lead you to like humility
would be ways to avoid error right and
so what i want to say is like
okay yeah great maybe that's good if you
really want to avoid error if you really
care a lot about that but like
thing i care about is like being able to
know my errors
um and that's i i think that could also
go by the name of humility it's just a
different kind of humility and so maybe
it's worth
like it's sort of worth distinguishing
two kinds of humility right there's a
kind of humility that's almost like a
sort of invulnerability
where you kind of detach and you don't
think things so that you won't be wrong
um and as i say you're still not going
to avoid certain version of morse
paradox
but i'm looking for the kind of humility
where you don't detach where you do
commit and you think things and they're
wrong and you know that
all right um and just
stop me ignis if you want to pivot to
the second part because we've got a
bunch of questions
okay uh david north you're up
oh is his mic is not connected okay so
i'll
uh read it i wonder what agnes thinks
about this issue and the socratic method
for an argument sometimes you have to
suspend your personal beliefs for the
sake of argument
for myself this often means making
assertions i think are false but still
believe
in the context of the argument if agnes
is right about the paradox
how is the suspension which is necessary
for argument even possible
yeah good um
i'm not sure that what we do when we
argue is suspend judgment so this
gets to i'll talk more about this in the
socratic
part in the second half because that
sort of gets to the solution
um but like we use this phrase
suspension
a lot um um
like there's a thing that i do
say okay say i'm teaching hume right
hume's a philosopher i don't agree
with him about a lot of stuff um that's
why i picked him
um but when i'm teaching hume i try to
become human and like i try to become
persuaded by hume and i'm arguing
like you know like i'm i'm trying to see
the world
the way someone sees it who doesn't see
causal connections as like really being
there as being in things and there's
just a bunch of things following one
another and i'm like i'm like
trying to inhabit that point and it it's
like have i suspended
um my my standard beliefs about
causation
i'm not even sure what they are like
it's more like
now i'm hume for a bit um and i in a way
i really believe those things for like a
little while anyways
um so i guess i'm less sure that what
happens in philosophy
is that we like suspend anything um
um maybe um the backdrop here is
um i think that our beliefs are not very
stable
and we have an illusion of a lot more
belief stability than is in fact
that is than what is in fact present and
so
um there you don't need to do that much
suspending you're just flip-flopping all
the time
right and so i can just be hume for a
little while because my views about
causation aren't very like well fixed
um and so i guess i'm inclined to think
what happens in philosophy is more like
wavering and also more like sincere
belief than like the suspension of
judgment
um uh and why do i think that
well this gets it something that will
take us like maybe i may i might not
have time to get into but i think a lot
of the questions that we talk about
especially in socratic dialogues right
so david referred to surprise dialogues
questions about justice uh you know what
it is to be a good person
what kind of life i want to live
those questions are too important to us
to suspend judgment on like we kind of
can't do it
um and that's actually characteristic of
a lot of philosophical questions
uh so we we jump to conclusions on those
questions
immediately um uh it's
um uh and
and so it's not it's not clear to me
that with those questions suspension of
judgment is an option i can talk more
about that but that's like a that's like
a big territory
that i maybe want to wait and see if
other people ask about because i would
go on at length
there's some cool questions uh rob hart
you have a question
let me scroll back and find it does
morris paradox have space for the
unconscious or
sort of half conscious intuition that i
sometimes feel that i'm
wrong about something i don't know what
it is yet but like i just know that in
the back of my head something's calling
the alarm and saying you're wrong check
your first principles
yeah good um so like
um i think one of the ways that we often
try to get out of contradictions is like
sort of like to create a
distinction or division right um in the
self even right so you're like
well i believe p but like a part of me
doesn't
there's like a little voice or a little
like another person
right and
um i think that
there's like kind of like as a
theoretical or conceptual
question i really wonder to what extent
those moves make sense like
they we verbally we verbally invoke them
so as to not be asserting a
contradiction right so as to not be like
i believe this but i don't believe it
um and so we're like a part of me
doesn't believe it right
but if we take like the word unconscious
literally say
like freud's unconscious is unconscious
right you're not supposed to be you're
not supposed to be able to like hear
what it says
so okay we don't mean unconscious we
mean i kind of think this thing that i
also don't think at the same time um
and so like there's this question what
like what is that and i do
think that if you could if you could
come up with a really good theory of
that
a really good account of what it would
mean to doubt the very thing that you
are thinking
um i think that would be the beginnings
of a real response
um but there's but you need to do more
work than just to say
well there's this other voice because
it's like like one way i could hear
voices is like
i could be like this is weird i'm
hearing voices right like
like someone else's voices are in my
head and that's not what you're talking
about you're talking about hearing your
own voice right you're talking about
like no this is me
saying that this is a mistake right and
so like i'm saying it's not a mistake
and i'm saying it is a mistake and it's
one me
right speaking with two voices um
so like one way to hear that is
vacillation right
it's like i think it's right and then a
second later like no wait a minute and
then another second later yeah it's
right
right so temporal vacillation is one way
to
like get the logic clean there but if
you have temporal vacillation you
haven't solved my problem right because
it's like you always think you're right
at any given moment it's just that you
keep changing your mind
and so what you need in order to really
get a grip on the problem is this idea
that simultaneously you could have this
voice
it would be your voice it wouldn't be
you know it wouldn't be like i'm hearing
voices right
your voice um uh
and um and you would
you know you would take it seriously but
it wouldn't represent
sort of you know your like main view
right so i i guess what yeah what i want
to say is like that's that's promising
maybe you could get it to work
um that would be the kind of thing like
i think that's
that's what we mean by a solution is
that sort of thing
there's two good questions i wanted to
flag uh ryan you got a question on the
collective intelligence
i'll post it below for you
okay yourself yeah so
i mean this doesn't solve the problem
but if you kind of expand to collective
intelligence
do you minimize the problem because the
chance of me and you both being right is
wrong as less than the chance of just
myself being wrong
um so
so i think that uh if
a lot of people agree with me
about some proposition
then um the chances
that then it's reasonable especially if
it's like an empirical proposition
then like it's reasonable for me to
think
that um
we're probably correct or something like
that like that it's unlikely that i'm
wrong about that one on the other hand i
still might be wrong
right a lot of people can agree and be
wrong and then it would be like extra
bad
so that kind of um uh
but like that doesn't um
i suppose it doesn't really help because
um
what what that might help you with is
um you know identifying zones of
relative safety
like i'm relatively safe on this one
because a lot of people agree with me
but suppose i want to know what i'm
wrong about right
well maybe i should gravitate towards
the the ones where a few people agree
with me
but i have that i have views that few
people agree with me about
and i think those views are true i think
i'm right about those things
i wouldn't have those views if i didn't
think they were true right
so um it's not like i can go over to the
domain
where my view isn't shared by many
people and be like oh that's what i'm
wrong about because if i thought i was
wrong about that i would just change my
mind
and so you know i feel like this
observation
about like um collective you know
the group agreement is really more like
in the domain of that kind of like
metacognitive take a step back and be
like oh
if i'm wrong about anything it's
probably one of these ones that few
people agree with me about
by contrast with one of these ones that
a lot of people agree with me about but
i don't think i'm wrong about any of it
if i did i wouldn't believe it
cool um aj you had a question
um hey jake yeah so hi
um so i guess
kind of still sympathetic to your 16
year old's
initial reaction that you reported at
the beginning
um like i'm i'm still having like a hard
time seeing why we should
be so worried about this like it it
seems to me like
you can accept the considerations
that give rise to this situation that we
can't
know that we're wrong while we're wrong
and
still like be able to say
like okay i was wrong right up to the
very instant where i
realized that i used to be wrong and
that seems like enough
to be able to like um
enable us to engage in like practices of
self-correction
and so on um and like i think you raised
a worry
um towards the beginning of your like
initial remarks
about self-knowledge um
but i guess i don't know
it's um like it's hard for me to feel
the
force of that like like i think the um
the like
identifying other people by their errors
is sort of a disordered practice
that is bad like like i do it too but
um i i think it's like probably
fortunate that we don't like identify
ourselves in that way
um so like yeah i
i would be interested you could maybe
just like say a bit more
to like rebut um
like quietest like arguments for not
worrying about the issue yeah
good i'm not sure i'll have enough to
satisfy you but
so one thing is like
um i guess it's like being wrong
is one of the fundamental human
experiences
and yet i don't get to undergo it so
like um like you know
sort of arguably like the the the main
kind of like um
uh i don't know
what makes a person a person is that she
has a power to represent the world
right so we have each of us has this
like picture of
the world like that we take around with
us everywhere we go
um like if you didn't understand that
people have that that everyone has in
their head a kind of map of reality
right you would not understand people
because that's like a really deep fact
about people
um but all of us are
you know mismapping reality in a bunch
of different ways right
and those distortions like
the distortions in my perspective
those are just as much a part of me as
the perspective itself and in a way
they they um they are what like
um make my perspective
um kind of distinctive and individual i
don't mean they're the only thing they
make an individual right but they're
like
um they they there's a reason why they
serve to individuate
me to other people and so it's like
this map that i have of the world
like it has these proper it's like it's
me in some sense it has these properties
that i'm not able to like be aware of
and so it's like i'm
i'm i'm you know it's like a part of my
life is going unlived by me
um and i i want to agree with you aj
that like
even if that part of my life always went
unlived by me
i could still engage in practices of
correction and stuff like to improve the
map
right so i don't want to insist
that um being able to be aware of being
wrong is somehow essential to going
right to coming to go right
um it might be for some questions i
think it is but but for many questions
it isn't
so but i just have like an independent
desire to sort of know this
um and so i guess i think like
you know the identifying people by their
errors it isn't just like we're negative
and we like to be critical of people
it's something about the
um the process of individuation right
like if you just saw
the map of reality as being identical to
reality that wouldn't individuate anyone
right um everyone has their own bit of
it and that's like that's what makes
them distinctive and yet for me
i like conflate in some way my map of
reality with reality it's like so i
don't
see myself um so it's that kind of it's
the kind of self-knowledge i guess that
i'm looking for that i think is valuable
and important
um and i think of it as intrinsically
valuable
and you know you might think um
maybe maybe an analogy might be like
there are certain pains of loss the loss
of a loved one
the end of a relationship right where
you feel this hurt of losing something
that was valuable to you
and you might not want to not feel that
that is
you like feeling that feeling that
you're missing this thing that's really
good and valuable to you
is like really important human
experience right
um you wouldn't take a pill to make
your the pain of mourning go away
under circumcision certainly as you
might but you wouldn't always
necessarily take it right
and that's because you want to
experience that you it's part of what it
is to be you that that loss is really
happening and you want
to have like the kind of awareness part
of it
to yourself and so i'm saying i want
that with being wrong i want the
awareness part
um and um you know so it's like i feel
like i'm being forced to take that pill
the pill where i don't feel it and even
if it would be painful i would want it
um maybe we should go up should we what
do you think peter should we take maybe
one more question and then go on to the
second part
uh yeah um i i have a question that kind
of
uh could piggyback what aj just said um
about like how seeing it may not be a
problem
um so that whole kind of like problems
that this is just a given
of human you know existence and then we
have to rely on
corrective mechanisms like the socratic
method um
to kind of divide the epistemic labor um
but also kind of like what we do here in
stowe we engage in all these kind of we
space intersubjective practices so
what's your thoughts on the extension of
the sense of self
in order to respond to this issue yeah
good
so that that really does get to my
um solutions so i'll quickly
give you my old solution which i still
think is
you can solve this problem in more than
one way right um
so uh and then i'll give you the
solution i'm working on now so my first
book is called aspiration
and it's about like the process of
trying to become a better person
but better in some concrete way like
better at appreciating classical music
or
a better parent or a better student or
um you know um
um yeah better at like a sport right
um so you know but specifically where
part of what it means to become better
is to more
fully grasp the domain of value
that is that you know that domain right
so
like really coming to see
what it is for something to be well done
in the domain of say
sports or something like that okay so
the book is about that process and
what i argue is that when you're sort of
underway
like and you're sort of coming to
appreciate it more and more
then you kind of know that you don't
fully appreciate it
right you you can see that you're
missing stuff
and so and some of the way that that
shows up
is you feel kind of bad about yourself
like you
um you know you're you're like listening
to classical music but you're like
getting distracted every like three
minutes because it's kind of boring
and you but you're like yeah but it's
not boring
actually i'm the one who's screwed up
i'm not appreciating it like
i'm failing to grasp the value that is
really there
i think that is a way of realizing that
you're wrong
it's not a mistake and belief exactly
right so it's not a super great solution
um but it is uh um
uh it's the absence of a belief right
it's like there's a belief i should have
that i don't have
um about the value of this thing so it's
not that i have a false belief exactly
but it's that i fail to have a true one
and i can tell that i fail to have it i
can tell i'm missing
something and part of how i can tell i'm
missing it is just my sense
that i'm moving myself forward into a
future in which i will have a better
grasp
okay that's like my first book was about
this problem only i didn't put it this
way
but now i'm interested in and that's
that's a kind of diacronic
like it's a it's a way of saying let's
spread the agent through time and she
can look sort of
she can look from the point of view of
the present into the future and say then
in the future i'm gonna fully know
and so by thinking in that way she can
think to herself in the present i don't
fully there's something wrong with me
now i can tell i can feel it
she can even feel kind of shame and
embarrassment um
in not getting it right okay so that's
one that's one way i think we can be
aware of being wrong
it's through aspiration the way i'm and
i'm happy to entertain questions on that
if you guys have questions thoughts
but the way i'm interested in right now
it has to do with the socratic method
so i think that one way to see the
socratic method
is that like before this presentation i
was sitting here in my office and i was
thinking through these thoughts right
and i was doing it by myself
and i'm like oh yeah this is pretty
persuasive this is a good point you know
talking to myself right
uh i'm i am we all are
amazing orators of ourselves like when
we speak to ourselves we are so easily
persuaded
right so i'm like oh this is good
thinking that i'm doing right
um socrates says in the theaters
and actually also same similar line jobs
in this office
that thinking is like a conversation one
has with oneself
but like it's like a conversation with
somebody who's like just
claps every time after you say
everything like yeah great
and i think that like
right now what i'm trying to do is
persuade you right so i'm not trying to
persuade me anymore
um i have a much harder target like i
have to convince you guys
right that um what right
well that you're doing a kind of
thinking with me right now
like um you're playing the role of me
in the conversation i had with myself
right i've now
taken that slot but speaking to myself
i'm not speaking to you
and um i think what that means is like
we're thinking
together so the subject of the thought
is
both of us but suppose you're not
persuaded
i think that's me being wrong and i can
tell i'm wrong
because you're not persuaded and you're
like no that doesn't seem right
to me and i try another argument right
and this gets back to like david's
question about the sort of socratic
method
um and um it's
you know um whatever it is that i'm
trying to persuade you of
at that moment i think it even if maybe
you know
before i didn't right um and
i am pushing that line i'm not just
adopting that view for the sake of
argument or something i mean
i'm pushing it as hard as i can i'm
doing everything i can to think the
thoughts that i'm thinking
and you're pushing back
and that i think
you know you're arguing against me and
being unpersuaded by what i'm saying
is a way for me to know that i'm wrong i
won't say anything more than that for
now because i want to hear your thoughts
about that and i can flush it out in the
conversation
thomas uh cleveland you got a question
yeah you said um that if the
other person fails to be persuaded that
means you know you're wrong
isn't it possible that the other person
is wrong and you are right
or did i misunderstand you good
um so um
i think that um
um there are two different reasons why
they might be unpersuaded
one um
they might be deliberately like not
listening to you
they might have like bad motives they
might write so sometimes you're talking
to someone
and you think the reason i'm not
persuading them
is just that like they came into this
like they literally had plugs in their
ears right they're not hearing anything
i'm saying or whatever so there are
cases like that
those are quite rare um uh
you know and um
as long as that's not happening
if i know anything i should be able to
teach it to you
it doesn't matter whether you're like
you came into this maybe you were wrong
right but if i'm if i if i have
knowledge i should be able to give it to
you
so if i don't if i can't give it to you
um even though you're participating
you're cooperating you're listening
and you're just like no i'm not
convinced here's a problem whatever
then that's on me then that means i
didn't know what i thought i knew
it doesn't mean that my view is false so
that's
like um maybe what you're bringing out
here right
it doesn't follow that the view that i'm
trying to argue to you
is false but it does follow that i don't
know it
um if you know something you can teach
it
so um i do think that that's
um you know we get we at least get that
far in like
falling short there's a great moment in
the leki
lekies where socrates says has just
refuted
leki's definition of courage as
endurance
and he's about to move on but he's like
yeah and maybe courage is endurance
let's move on
and you're like wait you just refuted
that and he's like socrates like yeah i
refuted it
what that means is that i showed that
leki's didn't know that but it doesn't
mean courage can't it doesn't mean it's
false
it just means that leki's wasn't able to
teach it to us
right so yeah that's a fair point that
really
all all that i'm doing is experiencing
my own
inability to teach you something
just as a second point i'm remain
unpersuaded
because it seems possible to me that
let's assume that you're right about
something
maybe that's the best assumption uh and
um
there are defects of nature
or if you want to be more specific there
are opinion
alternative opinions the person you are
speaking to
is attached to in such a way that no
amount of speaking
will suffice even if the arguments
as given are the correct arguments
something like that
um so i mean you were you were
recognizing that as a possibility but it
just seems to me that's
a very live possibility that isn't due
to your failure
i agree so i here's a way that socrates
talks about this he says
someone can be a mirror to someone else
right
so when i'm trying to explain something
to you you can be a mirror to me
and when you're a mirror it's like you
let me see these things about myself
that otherwise i can't see
right and that's the problem that we're
dealing with is that there are these
facts about myself about my own
perspective that i can't get into view
it's like trying to look at my own eyes
right
well i could do it if i had a mirror
right and you could be the mirror
but you might be like a super cloudy
mirror or like a really crummy mirror
because you're so like obsessed with
whatever points you had coming into the
conversation and with
saying them that you don't actually
allow me to see myself
and i think socrates prided himself on
being an awesome mirror right he's like
that's the one thing i can do
is be the mirror and i think that he
thought of philosophical conversation
really as people being able to serve as
mirrors for one another and philosophers
are super good at this like if you give
a talk in a philosophy department
all of the questions are going to be
like here's why
that one thing you said is inconsistent
with that other thing you said i'm gonna
keep myself out of it
right that's being a mirror so i think
you're right
that um whether or not i can have this
experience
with someone else is a function
of how good a mirror they can be and so
you know part of the story here is we
want to be able to be
really good mirrors to other people um
and this is why i think for instance
like just in thinking in terms of
contemporary culture
debate is very unsocratic so you have a
debate
you have two people and each of them has
opinions
that's one too many sets of opinions
nobody's going to be anybody's mirror in
that situation right
what you need is like a situation where
there's only one set of opinions
and that's um that's sort of what i mean
by like there's just
one bit of thinking that's going on
right it's sort of
put in two bodies but there's one bit of
thinking um
but that's never going to take the form
of a debate so debate in some way is
un-philosophical
by this way of thinking
all right um john you're up next
you're gonna meet yourself
john bae
okay i will read it on his behalf
um in a context of a world that is
constantly changing
uh in all levels of micro environments
to macro environments
planets etc right or wrong is fluid
right
that has been said even if we are right
in the next second we might be wrong
next in the next
i think there are things that don't
change uh
slavery is wrong it was always wrong
it's not fluid
um uh mathematical facts have always
been true
so there's like a set of facts that are
fluid that change
um empirical facts right and
i think that um with respect to those
facts
um if we want to know how things stand
we have to um go check so if i do
like is it cold or where i'm at well i
have to go check something
interesting about that go check is that
i can suspend judgment there right
so i can be like i don't know
let me check and then i'll get back to
you right and i can spend this time
not knowing um
and so i think the world of like flux
and change
is also the world that we are sort of
comfortable
suspending judgment about but then there
are things like moral judgments
right like um is something just or
unjust
um where we are very quick in jumping to
conclusions
and that's not because we're somehow
arrogant or overconfident in those
domains
it's because those questions are urgent
to us in a way where we can't
live even a minute without the answer
we're
we're i think kind of literally living
on the answer the answer is part of how
we live and so we need the answer to be
there so we can live
um and i think moral questions are like
that
i don't think those things fluctuate but
we fluctuate
because we cut we give reflexive
immediate answers
but there isn't a lot of stability in
how we answer and so
though we're always giving an answer the
answer kind of shifts and changes i
noticed this you know
the first time i really noticed this
actually was when my oldest son
was like little and i would read him
children's books and like the moral
of the one book would be like
um be who you are and it's fine if
you're different
um and don't conform to what other
people expect of you and like the moral
of the next book is like sharing is
caring and like
rainbow fish gives a little one of his
colors to all the other fish so that
everybody can have a
little rainbow color on their thing like
versus elmer the elephant who keeps all
the rainbow to himself and he's supposed
to be just
like loved for being different right
it's like these two books are telling my
child contradictory things
so some of that fluctuation that we see
in how we respond to the world some of
it is that the world is fluctuating and
that's the empirical stuff but
other fluctuation is like we're screwed
up we don't have a
stable moral compass to guide us
uh and those sorts of mistakes
i think are ones that we should try to
stop making um
um because it's not true that
contradictory moral claims
are both correct it's just that like we
have a hard time getting our bearing and
so we're not giving consistent responses
so i guess
what i want to say is that i think that
um
you know there are very different kinds
of fluctuations
and some of them reflect defects in us
and some of them don't and the ones that
reflect defects in us
are precisely going to be
you know defects where we're sort of
taking ourselves
to know something to be able to give to
really have a thought through answer to
something where we don't have a thought
through answer we just have like a
reflexive quick response
cool uh stefan uh do you want to read
your question
uh sure all right so
basically i'm wondering you know there's
these different versions of us the today
me the right now me
and then there's that person yesterday
or yesteryear
and often that person before
makes a commitment for me to execute
if i don't execute who's the wrong one
the one who fails to execute or the one
who fails to anticipate that
you know i might not be in the mood or i
might not have tools or i
have this
good um i i
guess i think it could be either one um
so um
i think that um
it it might depend on whether we
take that little sort of that episode
and what is the larger story that it's
part of right so
um you know um
one kind of case is a case where
um let's say i'm weak willed right and
so i'm like
um oh i should you know
go to bed early because in the morning i
have this thing i have to do
and i know that i should do that but
then when the time comes right
i flip right and i'm like oh i just feel
like staying up a little more
um and then you want to say okay what's
the bigger picture the bigger picture
here
is um you know my real commitments or
something
are it could go either way actually but
let's just tell the story where the real
commitment is
that i am um
you know this thing was really important
to me and i really should have gone to
bed and then it's like i failed in the
moment
right and we do fail the moment so like
um but we would need that bigger
diachronic story because
it could go otherwise too you know
there's you could tell a story where
like
somebody is like in grad school and like
they keep on
just getting distracted and like not
doing their work and they're so like
angry at themselves
but like um um
this happened to me um like in many
different stages of grad school
um i was in classics i was like trying
to be a classicist you know and
but i was spending all my time reading
freud i spent like a year just like
reading through the works of freud and
going into
analysis and i'm like this is crazy i
should i'm a classicist i'm still
reading greek there's not supposed to be
doing
um but um you know i'm like oh this is
so akratic of me right
but in fact it was like well that was
like kind of a bad theory of myself
because i didn't
end up as a classicist i ended up as
somebody where these questions about
the division of the self and the
unconscious were really deeply gripping
me
and my weakness of will was in fact the
beginning of my inquiry into a certain
thing that i couldn't quite see that
that's what it was
a lot of times when we're weak willed
that's because
we have a bad theory about what like the
main background state of ourselves is
right and
we're actually sort of aspiring to be a
slightly different person and so i think
that
if you want to know like who's right
who's wrong
and you kind of need that longer story
and what that us
what also you know follows from that is
like if you only have the shorter bit of
the story you just might not be able to
know
and could be a little bit of both
there's a little bit of
this communicate obviously in this
communication so they're both both wrong
to a certain degree
yes i think that yes
in fact i think that in all of the cases
they're both going to be wrong
there's just a question of who's more
wrong
because like you know that background
perspective of prudence or whatever that
tells me i should go to bed early
it's like if i really knew that i agree
with socrates on this that if i really
knew that and i had really reasoned that
out firmly and it
really had taken a hold of my soul then
i wouldn't be tempted
so obviously there's something wrong
with how i'm gripping that and so even
that is like wrong um
um in the sense that i don't fully grasp
it in the way that i take myself to
so yeah i think that they're both
somewhat wrong yeah go ahead and just
last follow-up and then when there's
nuts like that but let's say there's
just two
two goods that are in conflict and you
just can't possibly
do both or they're just you know so
is that the same situation or there's
conflicting goods and
one as opposed to sort of like the
crazier grazia
yeah i think that's really different um
so i think that the difference is that
in um in the case of
akrazia weakness of will we um
take ourselves to know quite firmly
which of the two things we ought to
pursue we might be wrong about it
but we take ourselves to know it um
whereas if i'm torn between two options
um both of which look good to me
right um i have not yet completed
the deliberative process that theocratic
takes herself to be at the end of
or maybe i never will right maybe i'll
just have to pick or something but still
accuracy is not possible until you've
completed that process cool
um so we have about four minutes do you
want to close it here do you want to
sneak in another
question let's get another question okay
uh
kevin deland you had a question if
you're to mute yourself
kevin
okay
there's uh okay so that's just a joke
okay um i thought you had a question
about kevin but i'll read someone else's
question
does the fact that experts in science
philosophy et cetera disagree mean that
they cannot teach
convince each other that therefore they
have no knowledge
um so um
with respect to science yes that would
be true i think
um but it's not true about science um
the experts don't disagree
uh they might disagree on like points of
detail right where which is lies at the
margin of the field
right um and that's exactly the stuff
that they don't know yet
right the stuff that they are
disagreeing about philosophy is really
different
so um uh in the case of philosophy
there is um
no possibility that
um someone can like do it for you
in the sense that people can kind of do
your scientific thinking for you like
people do most of our scientific
thinking for us right so they like
you know everything i think about like
matter is is stuff i don't really know
but i'm
it's like i trust you know the
scientists tell me this is how it goes
and i trust them and there's some fancy
math and some experiments that i don't
know about
um but like i've sort of like farmed it
out right
so that's the nature of scientific
thinking is that it can be farmed out to
experts
and the experts had better agree because
that's part of how we know who to farm
it out to
um but in philosophy the experts don't
agree but also we can't farm it out
so um uh it's like suppose
like i'm like you know like i'm talking
to you about knowing that you're wrong
and i have this view but like you have
to come to see it for yourself you have
to
you you can't just you can't defer to me
right you can't be like well i'll just
adopt her views
um and so
in effect um you know
if i um
me kind of like counting as knowing and
me
being able to persuade you and you
seeing it for yourself like those were
all three of the same thing
there's no thing where like i just kind
of say it and you take it up without
fully grasping it for yourself and so in
effect
because anyway there's no shortcut
around you knowing it for yourself
from your point of view like whether i
know it or not shouldn't be that
interesting or important to you right
can you learn from me is the question
um so you know yes philosophers
disagree among themselves and um
uh but we can still serve as mirrors for
one another right and we do that
and it's still just true that if you
want to know something
you have to sort of like find someone
you can inquire with so that you can
come to see it for yourself and even if
we
knew all the answers we couldn't solve
the problems for you
um so um
uh yeah i guess that's
um that's what i'd say about that
so that's a there's a long topic we
could go on for a long time but that's a
quick answer
very cool um so we're almost at the hour
now uh
let's close it up here i thought that
was really fun uh and i really enjoyed
the kind of the two partners and i might
even do like a philosophical problem
question thing at the store where people
pose a really rich philosophical
question people just kind of like
respond to it
but do you have any closing thoughts uh
for us before i make closing
announcements
closing thoughts um
no
cool so uh i'll make some closing
announcements uh agnes thanks so much
for coming to stowe today this will be
on youtube later in the day so you can
share it look at it
review it so upcoming events at the stoa
we have tons of events you can check on
the website tomorrow we have a series
called the philosopher
queens uh with rachel haywire and raven
connolly and nina power
is coming in uh so rachel could you just
uh mute yourself and plug that
event that's happening tomorrow at 3 p.m
eastern time
hi so we're really excited about hosting
new
power at the philosopher queens here at
the stara tomorrow
if you guys know about nina power she's
an ex-academic
incredible philosopher and cultural
critic if you guys don't know justin
murphy
they're running an online course
together on the thai raven
and i are going to be speaking with nina
about
everything from sex and men to women
and controversy so please come by and
join us that philosopher queens
cool thank you rachel i post that in the
chat you can also go on the website
we also have a wisdom gym here and we
have all these interesting kind of
psychotechnology type stuff
there's a session called flowing with
unknowingness just imagine freestyle rap
and the socratic method just
mixed together um that's what you'll get
uh
tyson if you're here i believe wanna
wanna plug that for us
yeah thank you peter thank you agnes uh
yeah
diaphlogos is another new name for it
that has come up
and it's um having a group conversation
collective dialogue through freestyle
and it's an opportunity to come let
yourself be wrong
make mistakes be silly be embarrassed
whatever it is that comes up
let it come out and just have fun with
the spoken word
so no experience with freestyle rap is
necessary for you to have a great time
along with unknowingness that's mondays
at 8 30 eastern
thank you tyson and agnes that might be
the you know the solution to the problem
who knows
that the free stuff rap session and we
just uh
noam chomsky emailed me this morning
he's coming to stowa november
16th 5 30 p.m eastern time the
responsibility of intellectuals
so dope so excited about that
uh might be interviewed by daniel
schwagtenberger too so that should be
cool
uh i'll post uh the website uh
stoa.ca check it out support us on
patreon if you like what we're doing
here and you can sign up for the mailing
list
that being said agnes thank you so much
for visiting stoa
love to have you back everyone thank you
all thanks for coming today this is
really fun
bye thank you